I don't have a problem keeping myself
busy within the precepts. But when I
reflect on the value of those precepts,
the weight of my situation and of that
commitment becomes very heavy and
becoming overwhelmed. I stop with that
reflection. What should I do?
Well, the training is happening while
you're doing that reflection. So while
your mind feels confined by thinking
about permanently keeping the precepts,
that's when you're actually training. So
of course, breaking the precepts will
lead you to not just not do the
training, but actively go in the
opposite direction. So if you start
getting overwhelmed,
sure, stop reflecting on that, but don't
break the precepts.
So you pause the training, but you don't
start training the opposite thing.
And then whenever that kind of um overly
you know excessive pressure comes down
you'll be able to continue the same
reflection. And that's the difference
between keeping the precepts as um
external thing that you just happen not
to be doing while your mind is going
left and right. sometimes even
contemplating breaking the precepts
and keeping the precepts while that
internal boundary is firmly established
which exactly will result in that like a
sense of confinement and a sense of um
like actually having to give up those
possibilities versus just oh I'm not doing it right
versus just oh I'm not doing it right
now which is no different than a normal
person you know they spend 90% of their
time probably not breaking the precepts
But they never have to um confront the
the internal
recognition of I will not be able to do
this again. Like they will they would
only uh have to grapple with that if if
some external thing prevents them from
breaking the precepts. And then it's
like even if something external prevents
them, they would still be hoping for the
day where they can regain that
possibility. Like when you get sick, you
you're still anticipating even if you
can't, you know, pursue sensuality right
now, you're still hoping for the the day
where you'll be able to go back to it.
So the precepts will only be kept when
that door is completely closed. And
that's something that you internally
have to practice. It's not going to
happen by itself. the mind will will
still uh maintain those hopes to return
to what has been given up.
So that's why in the sutas um the the
Buddha would say the accomplishment in
virtue is when the mind is like um
becomes like a king who has defeated all
of its his enemies
like sees no danger in any direction in
the sense that now see it you don't need
to have an explicit plan that on such
and such a day on such a s such a time I
will give into sensuality
The fact that you're not sure that you
will never do it means the mind is not
established in virtue.
So establishing yourself in virtue
doesn't mean you know exactly what
you're going to do in advance. That's
impossible to know. But what you can
know for sure is
>> what am I intending not to do? And when
you intend not to break the precepts and
you see that there is no inclination to
do so either, then you can be sure that
that action will not happen regardless
of what the future holds. And that's a
certainty that you gain. You you
factually have no idea what will happen
tomorrow, but you know that this will
not be one of those things because I'm
intending not to do it and also there is
no craving to do it. Whereas
>> what if your mind starts craving to do
it? >> Well, that's that's exactly the like
>> Well, that's that's exactly the like
that craving is there. Why? Because
number one, you have been breaking the
precepts and number two, you have been
allowing the possibility of breaking the
precepts. So you don't need to like
imagine factually like an animal. You
don't need to let it go to where it
wants to go in order for it to be
agitated. You just need to allow the
hope that it will be able to go there.
So the hope is allowed automatically
by you not closing the door because
those actions are pretty much the the
path of least resistance. They're the
the the
pasture of your existence.
So
like just by not being free from
sensuality, not being free from ill
will, those actions are floating around
in your field of view so to speak. So if
you don't u determine not to do them,
you don't close the door to go towards
them, destroy the bridge as the Buddha
called it, then your the intention to do
them lingers even vaguely and that's
what keeps the mind craving to do them.
when it when all the hope is taken away.
Why? Because you reflected on the
danger. You reflected on how it's
factually better not to do those things.
Then that's how the craving will
disappear. But it's not a it's not a matter of you
But it's not a it's not a matter of you
doing that once. It's maintaining that
confinement up until for long enough the
door has been closed and the hope fades.
to ever go through it.
>> So, do you only do the training when the
dog is already agitated? You just wait
until it's agitated and then you that's
when you start teaching it.
>> Well, no. No. That's the thing.
>> That's when you close the door and the
rest of the time you leave it open.
That's the thing like you have to
essentially that that that is what the
right mindfulness is like those
simileies the Buddha gave where you
would uh keep like a bowl you would
avoid spilling even a drop of a bowl of
oil that you're carrying on your head
like it's not just that the animal has
to be agitated the mind has to be
agitated for you to to need to do those
reflections like I said your state of
being implies those actions because it's
still the sensual being. So you not
being clear that you will not do them
even if you're not actively planning to
do them
already means you're not you're you're
allowing the craving to survive.
So you have to live throughout your day
with the context that this will not be
done explicitly. You have to maintain
that perspective
because again if if if not breaking
precepts is
externally was would automatically
purify your mind and all you would have
to do is get some kind of disease that
makes you immobile and then you wouldn't
be you would become an arant eventually.
But that's not how it works because
internally you're still again allowing
that door leaving that door open.
And that's that's actually what even
monks would often not want to do to like
you know sure you spend 20 years in
robes and even if you die in robes you
never actually closed off the chance
that you could return to sensuality
eventually. So that's why unless you have the right
So that's why unless you have the right
perspective
that craving has to be given up because
it's the root of suffering you won't be
able to have right intention which is
intentional renunciation unconditional
renunciation like because you don't see the danger
like because you don't see the danger
cuz you're covering it up or not even
trying to reflect on it.
you won't be able to establish that
unconditional resolve cuz you're still
in doubt
that these actions are categorically unh
wholesome. So you need to clarify that first. You
So you need to clarify that first. You
need to understand why am I keeping
these precepts? Why am I restraining
myself? You don't need to arrive at some
uh you know
supercorrect theoretical answer.
It's like you can find different aspects
of what uh um kind of reflects that
danger, what what what um drawbacks you
can recognize from engaging in craving.
And you make sure that that is clear and
that as a result of that you keep the
precepts and then you'll be actually by
keeping the precepts you'll be wearing
away the craving.
It's like that that simile the Buddha
gave where you have a fire that's
burning with cart loads and cart loads
of wood
and then you don't uh you don't need to
like want for the fire to continue. All
you need to do is keep throwing fuel at
it. So you throw the fuel in the most
So you throw the fuel in the most
obvious way by breaking the precepts
and then in the less obvious way by not
being certain that you won't break them.
Like I said that keeps the door open.
But if you contemplate the danger and
automatically that that is what closes the door
that that is what closes the door
because you wouldn't want to engage in
something that is categorically against
your welfare.
So do you
wear the precepts
like how they can describe the satipanas
you know like a jacket.
>> So you wear the precepts and that wears
away the craving.
>> Yeah. You you you have to
as a sutribe you abide diligent, ardent
and resolute. You're not just like
floating around in limbo.
You keep that in mind. Why? Because it's
it's not even something that
like you're not keeping the precepts
harder by remembering that you won't break the
by remembering that you won't break the
precepts. How can you not do something
harder? So, it's not about adding to the
precepts. It's about demolishing the
bridge that you're already not crossing.
So it's just keeping that recognition of
this will not be done and that's like um
well like another simile the Buddha gave
like a hot pan where all the drops would
fall that would fall would immediately
just evaporate like any little intention
doesn't matter how fleeting it is to to
like oh maybe it will dissipate because
the door is completely closed it will
never be done. So instead of chasing
after the the little intentions that you
might think you need to to to pick out
individually, you see like, oh, all of those
you see like, oh, all of those
intentions, they can only exist if this
specific action is not completely
abandoned. Like why would you be thinking about
Like why would you be thinking about
what you're going to eat
if there's no food in the fridge?
If you if only if you forgot the fact
that there is no food,
would it make any sense for you to start
thinking about what you're going to eat?
>> Think about what color you're going to
paint your room if you have no room.
>> Yeah. And and it's like people would be
gener generally trying to to chase after
like, oh, this intention that came up
and I didn't see it or something.
>> It's like that's endless. It's going to
sneak in from whichever direction as
long as you're not clear about that
specific thing that will not be done
cuz it's all leaning in that direction.
Like it's it's not a these intentions
towards sensuality cannot be isolated.
They're always pointing towards an
individ to towards a specific action.
You can't be having sensual desire to to
I don't know touch a tree
like it's always yes it can it can uh
arise through different things through
subtler things but it's always because
that specific thing is not being
clarified as abandoned.
So all these little other things are
kind of steps slowly leading in that
direction that again would not be
happening if you were to be clear about
that specific thing being out of bounds.
speaking out of lust. Like why would you
have any interest in having harmless
little conversations with somebody
you're attracted to if you were to not
forget that you're celibate forever.
Any conversation you would have would
not be lustful. Like if it was
happening, it would be for some other
reason than lust. Only when see again
you're not necessarily planning towards
intercourse or towards any kind of unh
wholesome action. You're just
[clears throat] not being clear this
will not be done. Leaving it ambiguous
makes the lust able to land
again even if you don't do anything at
the end.